<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R5/fhir-single.xsd">


  <h4>I. RATIONALE</h4>
  <div>
    <p>The Philippine Integrated Disease Surveillance and Response (PIDSR) of the Epidemiology
      Bureau
      (EB) is an integrated approach for strengthening the Philippine epidemiologic surveillance and
      response system. It was established in 2007 following the International Health Regulations
      (THR)
      call for a stronger surveillance system.</p>

    <p>The Public Health Surveillance Division (PHSD) of EB supports the Republic Act (RA) No. 11223
      “Universal Health Care (UHC) Act” and RA No. 11332 "Mandatory Reporting of Notifiable Diseases
      and Health Events of Public Health Concern Act" thus, PIDSR is hereby enhanced to integrate
      Epidemic-prone Disease Case Surveillance (EDCS) and Event-based Surveillance and Response
      (ESR)
      surveillance activities and response at all level of Epidemiology and Surveillance Units
      (ESUs).
      The province-wide and city-wide health systems for the delivery of population-based health
      services need to establish accurate, sensitive, and timely epidemiologic disease surveillance
      systems as stipulated in Chapter IV, Section 17 of the UHC Act. Moreover, the enhancement of
      PIDSR is in compliance with the World Health Organization (WHO) recommendations on its
      external
      assessment of the surveillance system in 2019</p>

    <p>As part of the enhancement, EDCS and ESR shall be under the PIDSR as indicated in Rule V,
      Section 1 and Rule VIII, Section 1 of the 2020 Revised Implementing Rules and Regulations
      (IRR)
      of RA 11332, as the early warning system for epidemics. The EDCS includes surveillance of
      epidemic-prone diseases from the sentinel sites (AO No. 2018-0023 "Guidelines in Strengthening
      the Capacity of Public Health Units of DOH Hospitals and All Level Three Hospitals (Government
      and Private) on Sentinel Surveillance System for Notifiable Diseases of Epidemic Potential")
      and
      non-sentinel sites, while ESR shall capture other health events of public health concerns and
      provides information for International Health Regulations (IHR) notification.</p>

    <p></p>
    <p></p>
  </div>
  <h4>II. OBJECTIVES</h4>
  <div>
    <p>This Order aims to provide an enhanced PIDSR to guide its implementation at all levels of the
      health care delivery system in both the public and private sectors.</p>

    <p></p>
    <p></p>
  </div>
  <h4>III. SCOPE OF APPLICATION</h4>
  <div>
    <p>This Order shall apply to DOH Central Office bureaus and units, DOH Centers for Health
      Development (CHDs), DOH Hospitals including the Bangsamoro Autonomous Region in Muslim
      Mindanao
      (BARMM) subject to the applicable provisions of RA 11054 or the “Bangsamoro Organic Act”, and
      shall cover all levels surveillance and response activities.</p>
    <p></p>
    <p></p>
  </div>
</div>